I think we have to do something about a culture, a piece of the culture of medicine that has
to change, and I think it starts with one physician, and that's me, and maybe I've been
around long enough that I can afford to give away some of my false prestige to be able
to do that.
Before I actually begin the meat of my talk, let's begin with a bit of baseball.
Hey, why not?
We're near the end.
We're getting close to the World Series, right?
We all love baseball, don't we?
Baseball is filled with some amazing statistics, and there's hundreds of them.
Moneyball is about to come out, and it's all about statistics and using statistics to build
a great baseball team.
I'm going to focus on one stat that I hope a lot of you have heard of.
It's called batting average.
So we talk about a batter who bats 300.
That means that ball player batted safely, hit safely three times out of ten at bats.
That means hit the ball into the outfield, it drops, it didn't get caught, and whoever
tried to throw to first base didn't get there in time, and the runner was safe.
Three times out of ten.
Do you know what they call a 300 hitter in Major League Baseball?
Good.
Really good.
You know, maybe an all-star.
Do you know what they call a 400 baseball hitter?
That's somebody who hit, by the way, four times safely out of every ten.
Legendary.
As in Ted Williams' legendary, the last Major League Baseball player to hit over 400 during
a regular season.
Now let's take this back into my world of medicine where I'm a lot more comfortable,
or perhaps a bit less comfortable, after what I'm going to talk to you about.
Suppose you have appendicitis, and you're referred to a surgeon who's batting 400 on
appendectomies.
Somehow this isn't working out, is it?
Now suppose you live in a certain part of a certain remote place, and you have a loved
one who has blockages in two coronary arteries, and your family doctor refers that loved one
to a cardiologist who is batting 200 on angioplasties.
But, but, you know what, she's doing a lot better this year.
She's on the comeback trail, and she's hitting 257.
Somehow this isn't working, but I'm going to ask you a question.
What do you think a batting average for a cardiac surgeon or a nurse practitioner or
an orthopedic surgeon, an OBGYN, a paramedic, is supposed to be?
One thousand.
Very good.
Okay.
Now, the truth of the matter is, nobody knows in all of medicine what a good surgeon or
physician or paramedic is supposed to bat.
What we do, though, is we send each one of them, including myself, out into the world
with the admonition, be perfect.
Never, ever, ever make a mistake, but you worry about the details, about how that's
going to happen.
And that was the message that I absorbed when I was in med school.
I was an obsessive-compulsive student.
In high school, a classmate once said that Brian Goldman would study for a blood test.
And so I did.
I studied in my little garret at the nurse's residence at Toronto General Hospital not
far from here, and I memorized everything.
I memorized in my anatomy class the origins and insertions of every muscle, every branch
of every artery that came off the aorta, differential diagnoses, obscure and common.
I even knew the differential diagnosis and how to classify renal tubular acidosis.
And all the while, I was amassing more and more knowledge.
And I did well.
I graduated with honors, cum laude.
And I came out of medical school with the impression that if I memorized everything
and knew everything or as much as possible, as close to everything as possible, that it
would immunize me against making mistakes.
And it worked for a while until I met Mrs. Drucker.
I was a resident at a teaching hospital here in Toronto, and Mrs. Drucker was brought to
the emergency department at the hospital where I was working.
At the time, I was assigned to the cardiology service, cardiology rotation.
And it was my job when the emergency staff called for a cardiology consult to see that
patient in emerge and to report back to my attending.
And I saw Mrs. Drucker, and she was breathless, and when I listened to her, she was making
a wheezy sound, and when I listened to her chest with a stethoscope, I could hear crackly
sounds on both sides that told me that she was in congestive heart failure.
This is a condition in which the heart fails, and instead of being able to pump all the
blood forward, some of the blood backs up into the lungs.
The lungs fill up with blood, and that's why you have shortness of breath.
And that wasn't a difficult diagnosis to make.
I made it, and I set to work treating her.
I gave her aspirin.
I gave her medications to relieve the strain on her heart.
I gave her medications that we call diuretics, water pills, to get her to pee out the excess
fluid.
And over the course of the next hour and a half or two, she started to feel better, and
I felt really good.
And that's when I made my first mistake.
I sent her home.
Actually I made two more mistakes.
I sent her home without speaking to my attending.
I didn't pick up the phone and do what I was supposed to do, which was to call my attending
and run the story by him so he would have a chance to see her for himself.
And he knew her.
He would have been able to furnish additional information about her.
Maybe I did it for a good reason.
Maybe I didn't want to be a high maintenance resident.
Maybe I wanted to be so successful and so able to take responsibility that I would do
so and I would be able to take care of my attending's patients without even having to
contact him.
The second mistake that I made was worse.
In sending her home, I disregarded a little voice deep down inside that was trying to
tell me, Goldman, not a good idea.
Don't do this.
In fact, so lacking in confidence was I that I actually asked the nurse who was looking
after Mrs. Drucker, do you think it's okay if she goes home?
And the nurse thought about it and said, very matter of factly, yeah, I think she'll do okay.
I can remember that like it was yesterday.
And so I signed the discharge papers and an ambulance came.
Paramedics came to take her home.
And I went back to my work on the wards.
All the rest of that day, that afternoon, I had this kind of gnawing feeling inside
my stomach.
But I carried on with my work and at the end of the day, I packed up to leave the hospital
and walk to the parking lot to take my car and drive home.
When I did something that I don't usually do, I walked through the emergency department
on my way home.
And it was there that another nurse, not the nurse who was looking after Mrs. Drucker before,
but another nurse said three words to me that are the three words that most emergency physicians
I know dread.
Others in medicine dread them as well, but there's something particular about emergency
medicine because we see patients so fleetingly.
The three words are do, you, remember.
Do you remember that patient you sent home?
The other nurse asked matter of factly.
She's back in just that tone of voice.
She was back all right.
She was back in near death.
About an hour after she had arrived home, after I'd sent her home, she collapsed and
her family called 911 and the paramedics brought her back to the emergency department where
she had a blood pressure of 50, which is in severe shock and she was barely breathing
and she was blue.
And the emergency staff pulled out all the stops, they gave her medications to raise
her blood pressure, they put her on a ventilator.
And I was shocked and shaken to the core and I went through this roller coaster because
after they stabilized her, she went to the intensive care unit and I hoped against hope
that she would recover.
And over the next two or three days, it was clear that she was never going to wake up.
She had irreversible brain damage.
And the family gathered and over the course of the next eight or nine days, they resigned
themselves to what was happening at about the nine day mark they let her go.
Mrs. Drucker, a wife, a mother, and a grandmother.
They say you never forget the names of those who die, and that was my first time to be
acquainted with that.
Over the next few weeks, I beat myself up and I experienced for the first time the unhealthy
shame that exists in our culture of medicine, where I felt alone, isolated, not feeling
the healthy kind of shame that you feel because you can't talk about it with your colleagues.
You know that healthy kind when you betray a secret that a best friend made you promise
never to reveal and you get busted and then your best friend confronts you and you have
terrible discussions, but at the end of it all, that sick feeling guides you and you
say, you know, I'll never make that mistake again and you make amends and you never make
that mistake again.
That's the kind of shame that is a teacher.
The unhealthy shame I'm talking about is the one that makes you so sick inside.
It is the one that says, not that what you did was bad, but that you were bad.
And it was what I was feeling and, you know, it wasn't because of my attending.
He was a doll.
He talked to the family and I'm quite sure he smoothed things over and made sure that
I didn't get sued.
And I kept asking myself these questions.
Why didn't I ask my attending?
Why did I send her home?
And then at my worst moments, why, why did I make such a stupid mistake?
Why did I go into medicine?
Slowly but surely it lifted.
I began to feel a bit better and, and you know, on a cloudy day there was a crack in
the clouds and the sun started to come out and I wondered, you know, maybe I could feel
better again.
And I made myself a bargain, you know, that if only I redoubled my efforts to be perfect
and never make another mistake again, please make the voices stop.
And they did.
And I went back to work and then it happened again.
Two years later, I was an attending in the emergency department at a community hospital
just north of Toronto and I saw a 25 year old man with a sore throat who was busy.
I was in a bit of a hurry.
He kept pointing here.
I looked at his throat.
It was a little bit pink and I gave him a prescription for penicillin and sent him on
his way.
And even as he was walking out the door, it was still sort of pointing to his throat.
And two days later I came to do my next emergency shift and that's when my chief asked to speak
to me quietly in her office and, and she said the three words, do you remember, do you remember
that patient you saw with the sore throat?
Well, it turns out he didn't have a strep throat.
He had a potentially life threatening condition called epiglottitis.
You can Google it, but it's an infection, not of the throat, but of the upper airway
and it can actually cause the airway to close.
And you know, fortunately he didn't die.
He was placed on intravenous antibiotics and he recovered after a few days.
And I went through the same period of shame and recriminations and felt cleansed and went
back to work until it happened again and again and again.
Twice in one emergency shift I missed appendicitis.
Now that takes some doing, especially when you work in a hospital that at the time saw
about 14 people at night.
Now in both cases, you know, I didn't send them home and I don't think there was any
gap in their care.
One I thought had a kidney stone.
I ordered a kidney x-ray when it turned out to be normal.
My colleague who, who was doing a reassessment of the patient noticed some tenderness in
the right lower quadrant and called the surgeons.
The other one had a lot of diarrhea.
I ordered some fluids to rehydrate him and asked my colleague to reassess him and he
did.
And when he noticed some tenderness in the right lower quadrant called the surgeons.
So in both cases they had their operations and they did okay.
But each time they were gnawing at me, eating at me.
And I'd like to be able to say to you that my worst mistakes only happened in the first
five years of practice, as many of my colleagues say, which is total BS.
Some of my doozies have been in the last five years.
Alone, ashamed and unsupported.
Here's the problem.
If I can't come clean and, and, and, and talk about my mistakes, if I can't find the still
small voice that tells me what really happened, how can I share it with my colleagues?
How can I teach them about what I did so that they don't do the same thing?
If I were to walk into a room, like right now I'm telling, I have no idea what you think
of me.
When was the last time you heard about somebody talk about failure after failure after failure?
Oh yeah, you go to a cocktail party and you might hear about some other doctor, but you're
not going to hear somebody talking about their own mistakes.
If I were to walk into a room filled with my colleagues and ask for their support right
now and start to tell what I've just told you right now, I probably wouldn't get through
two of those stories before they would start to get really uncomfortable.
Somebody would crack a joke, they changed the subject and we would move on.
And in fact, if I knew and my colleagues knew that one of my orthopedic colleagues took
off the wrong leg in my hospital, believe me, I'd have trouble making eye contact with
that person.
That's the system that we have.
It's a complete denial of mistakes.
It's a system in which there are two kinds of positions.
Those who make mistakes and those who don't.
Those who can't handle sleep deprivation and those who can.
Those who have lousy outcomes and those who have great outcomes.
And it's almost like an immunological reaction, like the antibodies begin to attack that person
and we have this idea that if we drive the people who make mistakes out of medicine,
what will we be left with but a safe system?
But there are two problems with that.
In my 20 years or so of medical broadcasting and journalism, I've made a personal study
of medical malpractice and medical errors to learn everything I can from one of the
first articles I wrote for the Toronto Star to my show White Coat Black Art.
And what I've learned is that errors are absolutely ubiquitous.
We live in a, we work in a system where errors happen every day, where one in ten medications
are either the wrong medication given in hospital or at the wrong dosage, where hospital-acquired
infections are getting more and more numerous, causing havoc and death.
In this country, as many as 24,000 Canadians die of preventable medical errors.
In the United States, the Institute of Medicine pegged it at 100,000.
In both cases, these are gross underestimates because we really aren't ferreting out the
problem as we should.
And here's the thing, in a hospital system where medical knowledge is doubling every
two or three years, we can't keep up with it.
Sleep deprivation is absolutely pervasive.
We can't get rid of it.
We have our cognitive biases so that I can take a perfect history on a patient with chest
pain, now take the same patient with chest pain, make them moist and garrulous and put
a little bit of alcohol on their breath, and suddenly my history is laced with contempt.
I don't take the same history.
I'm not a robot.
I don't do things the same way each time, and my patients aren't cars.
They don't tell me their symptoms in the same way each time.
Given all of that, mistakes are inevitable.
So if you take the system as I was taught and weed out all the error-prone health professionals,
well, there won't be anybody left.
You know that business about people not wanting to talk about their worst cases?
On my show on White Coat Black Arrow, I made it a habit of saying, here's my worst mistake.
I would say to everybody from paramedics to the chief of cardiac surgery, here's my worst
mistake, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, what about yours?
And I would point the microphone towards them, and their pupils would dilate, and they would
recoil.
They would look down and swallow hard and start to tell me their stories.
They want to tell their stories.
They want to share their stories.
They want to be able to say, look, don't make the same mistake I did.
What they need is an environment to be able to do that.
What they need is a redefined medical culture, and it starts with one physician at a time.
The redefined physician is human, knows she's human, accepts it, isn't proud of making mistakes,
but strives to learn one thing from what happened that she can teach to somebody else.
She shares her experience with others.
She's supportive when other people talk about their mistakes, and she points out other people's
mistakes, not in a gotcha way, but in a loving, supportive way so that everybody can benefit.
And she works in a culture of medicine that acknowledges that human beings run the system,
and when human beings run the system, they will make mistakes from time to time.
So the system is evolving to create backups that make it easier to detect those mistakes
that humans inevitably make, and also fosters in a loving, supportive way places where everybody
who is observing in the healthcare system can actually point out things that could be
potential mistakes and is rewarded for doing so, and especially people like me when we
do make mistakes, we're rewarded for coming clean.
My name is Brian Goldman. I am a redefined physician. I'm human. I make mistakes. I'm
sorry about that, but I strive to learn one thing that I can pass on to other people.
I still don't know what you think of me, but I can live with that. And let me close with
three words of my own. I do remember.